Guide to the Reference Center for Marxist Studies Pamphlet Collection PE.043
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Reference Center for Marxist Studies Pamphlet Collection
1900-2004
1940-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Reference Center for Marxist Studies
PE.043
48 Linear Feet 128 boxes and 3 folders in a shared manuscript box
The Reference Center for Marxist Studies (RCMS) was a radical library housed in the headquarters of the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA) in New York City. The Center was founded in the late 1970s or early 1980s. Its pamphlet collection consists of more than 10,000 pamphlets and includes nearly every pamphlet published by the CPUSA. It also includes pamphlets published by hundreds of organizations affiliated with or of interest to the CPUSA, and English language pamphlets published in the Soviet Union and other Communist countries. The pamphlets cover over 800 subject areas including: Communist Party activities throughout its history, anticommunism and the struggle against McCarthyism, the civil rights, labor and peace movements, the Spanish Civil War, anti-colonial and national liberation movements, and various Communist countries.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Reference Center for Marxist Studies, along with the Communist Party of the United States of America Records, in 2006. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.101.
Arrangement
The Reference Center for Marxist Studies (RCMS) Pamphlet Collection consists of over 10,000 pamphlets that are arranged alphabetically by subject. Subject headings were designated by the RCMS and retained in the arrangement of the collection. Each subject heading is a Series. Within each Series, the author, title, and publisher of only selected pamphlets are listed. Please note that not every pamphlet within the collection is listed.
Historical Note
The Reference Center for Marxist Studies (RCMS) was a radical library closely affiliated with the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Formed during the 1970s or early 1980s, it was located at the CPUSA headquarters in New York City. The RCMS library contained thousands of books, pamphlets, and serials devoted to the study of communism, the history of the CPUSA, socialism, the working class, African-Americans, women's issues, and national liberation struggles. Included were writings from a Marxist perspective on nearly every topic of historical and current interest. The RCMS was dedicated to serving the interests of students, scholars, political activists, community organizers, and trade unionists. The Center also sponsored cultural and educational programs, lectures, forums, and discussions.
The RCMS collection was formed through donations by American Marxists, labor leaders, and activists, as well as from the libraries of the Party-associated Jefferson School of Social Science and the Ruthenberg Library of its predecessor, the Workers' School, and from the CPUSA. One of the features of the library was its vast collection of pamphlets, categorized by over 800 subjects. Topics included: the activities of the CPUSA, including its early years, anti-communist movements, civil rights, the labor movement and individual labor unions, the peace movement, various Communist countries, and anti-colonial and national liberation movements. From the RCMS brochure about their collection of pamphlets, "the pamphlet collection is invaluable. It ranges from out-of-print 'penny pamphlets' of bygone activist days which have come out of closets onto our shelves to current issues relating to working class struggles."
The Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA), founded in 1919 by members of the left wing of the Socialist Party USA, played an important role in the labor movement, particularly in the building of the Congress of Industrial Organizations, in struggles for civil rights for African Americans, while its cultural initiatives attracted a number of prominent artists and intellectuals, and its struggles to attain and maintain its legality were an important chapter in the history of U.S. civil liberties.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Party of the USA Records (TAM 132)
Communist Party of the USA Photographs (PHOTOS 223)
Communist Party of the USA Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 031)
Scope and Content Note
The Reference Center for Marxist Studies Pamphlet Collection contains over 10,000 pamphlets and nearly every pamphlet published by the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). It also includes pamphlets published by hundreds of organizations affiliated with or of interest to the CPUSA. The pamphlets range in date from the late 19th century through to 2004, with the bulk published between 1940-1975. Prominently featured are hundreds of pamphlets from International Publishers, New Century Publishers, New Outlook Publishers, and Workers Library Publishers, all affiliated with the CPUSA. There are a sizable number of pamphlets published by the Novosti Press Agency Publishing House (Moscow) as well as the Party's newspaper, the, Daily Worker, later titled the Daily World, Party-associated cultural journal Masses and Mainstream, and the Party's monthly journal Political Affairs. Other publishers with pamphlets in the collection include Appeal to Reason, Charles H. Kerr and Company, New England Free Press, and Pioneer Publishers. Unions represented in the collection both as subjects, but also as publishers include, but are not limited to: the American Federation of Labor, the Congress of Industrial Organizations, the International Fur and Leather Workers Union, the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, the National Maritime Union, the United Automobile Workers, and the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE). The pamphlets are arranged by subject, designated by the Reference Center. Topics include: academic freedom, African-Americans, anti-communism (including the Smith Act and the United States Internal Security Act of 1950, aka the McCarran Act), civil rights, communism, fascism, Jews (including Jews in the Soviet Union, and the trial of Ethel and Julius Rosenberg), labor and labor unions, peace, the Spanish Civil War, the Vietnam War, women, World War I and World War II, and youth and youth organizations. There are files on countries from around the world, with pamphlets published by the Communist Parties of Canada, Great Britain, and the Soviet Union, as well as on Chile, China, Cuba, the German Democratic Republic (East Germany), North Korea, and Vietnam. Each file contains anywhere from one pamphlet up to thirty on a given topic. On certain topics, folders contain other printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, papers, constitutions, and newspaper clippings.
The collection is a rich source of information about the CPUSA, their writers and leaders, as well as their affiliate organizations, including the various incarnations of the Young Communist League, the Civil Rights Congress, and the International Workers Order. Pamphlets are illustrative and highlight positions that the CPUSA took on most of the major events of the 20th century. The Collection contains pamphlets written by Herbert Aptheker, Earl Browder, Georgi Dimitrov, William Z. Foster, Gus Hall, James Jackson, Vladimir Lenin, Mao Zedong, Robert Minor, George Morris, Pettis Perry, Paul Robeson, and Henry Winston, among countless others. There are pamphlets from the Jefferson School of Social Science (New York, N.Y.) and the Party's youth organization from 1970-1984, the Young Workers Liberation League. There are also pamphlets on and published by organizations such as the the Industrial Workers of the World and the League for Industrial Democracy. A majority of the pamphlets in the collection were published by presses or organizations based in New York, NY.
Each topic is listed as a series within the collection. Certain topics were selected by the processing archivist for further documentation. Pamphlets within these folders are listed and searchable by author, title, and publisher. Roughly half of the pamphlets within the collection are listed at the item level. However, the RCMS often put multiple copies of pamphlets within numerous folders. If possible to identify, the processing archivist did not repeat the pamphlet listing.
Bulletins.; Pamphlets.; Labor -- United States.; May Day.; Informers.; Scottsboro Trial, Scottsboro, Ala., 1931.; Sacco-Vanzetti Case.; Soviet Union -- History.; Soviet Union.; Fliers (printed matter); Social security.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Trotskyism.; Socialism; Clippings (information artifacts); Chile -- History -- 1970-1973.; Jews, Soviet.; Communist countries; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; Germany (East); Socialism and youth -- United States.; Communist parties; Rosenberg, Ethel, 1915-1953 -- Trials, litigation, etc; Rosenberg, Julius, 1918-1953 -- Trials, litigation, etc; Anti-communist movements -- United States.; Communism -- Soviet Union.; Korea (North); Unemployment insurance |z United States.; Russia -- History -- 20th century.; Working class; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Communism -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- African Americans.; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Communism -- United States -- 20th century; Communism -- China.; Communism -- Cuba.; Communism and culture -- United States.; Communism -- History.; African Americans -- History -- 20th century; Communism.; Communism -- Spain -- History.; Communists.; Communist trials -- United States.; Fascism.; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Housing -- United States.; Academic freedom -- United States; African American communists; African American communists -- History; Zionism.; World War, 1939-1945.; Civil rights.; Cold War.; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Communist Party of Great Britain; Communist Party of the United States of America; Kropotkin, Petr Alekseevich, kni︠a︡zʹ, 1842-1921; Aptheker, Herbert, 1915-2003.; Minor, Robert, 1884-1952; Browder, Earl, 1891-1973; Lumer, Hyman; Morris, George, 1903-; Ford, James W., 1893-1957; Perry, Pettis; Gerson, Simon W.; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; National Maritime Union of America; Young Workers Liberation League; League for Industrial Democracy; International Union, United Automobile Workers of America (CIO); International Fur and Leather Workers Union of the United States and Canada; American Federation of Labor; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich, 1870-1924; Dimitrov, Georgi, 1882-1949; Workers Library Publishers; International Publishers; Kommunisticheskaia partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza; United States. Internal Security Act of 1950; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976; Mao, Zedong, 1893-1976; Herndon, Angelo, 1913-1997; Hall, Gus; Jackson, James E., 1914-2007; Jefferson School of Social Science (New York, N.Y.); Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Trachtenberg, Alexander, 1884-1966; Starobin, Joseph R. (Joseph Robert), 1913-1976; Stalin, Joseph, 1878-1953; Sobell, Morton; AFL-CIO; Foster, William Z., 1881-1961; Winston, Henry, 1911-1986.; World Federation of Trade Unions; International Workers Order; Cacchione, Peter V., 1897-1947; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-; Davis, Benjamin J. (Benjamin Jefferson), 1903-1964; Marzani and Munsell (Firm); Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954; Allen, James S.; Jones, Claudia, 1915-1964.; Reference Center for Marxist Studies
- Abolition (4 pamphlets) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lawson, Elizabeth. Thaddeus Stevens: Militant democrat and fighter for Negro rights. International Publishers, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lawson, Elizabeth. Thaddeus Stevens. Elizabeth Lawson, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Academic Freedom (14 pamphlets) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Freedom and Academic Responsibility. American Civil Liberties Union, New York, NY., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Freedom in a Time of Crisis. New York Teachers Union, Local 555, United Public Workers of America, C.I.O., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sillen, Samuel. Cold War in the Classroom. Masses and Mainstream, Inc., New York, NY. (2 copies), 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Test of a Teacher: Professional Excellence of Political Conformity?. The Teachers Union, Local 555, United Public Workers, New York, NY. (2 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Gag on Teaching. American Civil Liberties Bureau, New York, NY., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Jerome Davis Case. American Federation of Teachers, Chicago, IL., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Weary, Gerald F. Democracy's Case Against Religious Education on School Time. Beacon Press, Boston, MA., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - What Kind of Teachers for Your Child. The Teachers Union, Local 555, United Public Workers, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Without Fear or Favor": the Case of the Michigan Students. Michigan Committee for Academic Freedom, Detroit, MI., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Zitron, Celia. No Ordinary Crisis: Schools in the Nixon Era. The Daily World, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Affirmative Action (3 pamphlets and material relating to the Weber case) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Why the Weber Case Concerns You... Trade Union Action and Democracy, Chicago, IL. (2 copies), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Afghanistan I (10 pamphlets) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1978-1988: Tenth Anniversay of April Revolution. Alberuni Publishing House, Kabul. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Afghanistan and Non-Aligned Movement. Government Printing Press., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Afghanistan: Darkness to Light. Liberation Publication., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ashraf, Mohammad. Afghanistan: A Difficult Path to Peace. Novosti Press Agency Publishing House, Moscow., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Babrak Karmal's Speeches. Democratic Republic of Afghanistan, Ministry of Information and Culture Publications Department., 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich. About the Events in Afghanistan: Leonid Ilyich Brezhnev's answers to questions by a correspondent of "Pravda." Grossbetrieb Volkerfreundschaft Dresden, Dresden, Germany., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bulganin, N.A. and N.S. Khrushchev. Visit to Burma and Afghanistan. New Century Publishers, New York., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bulganin, N.A. and N.S. Khrushchev. Report to the Supreme Soviet on the Visit to India Burma and Afghanistan. New Century Publishers, New York., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fratricide, No! Revolution, Yes! Government Printing Press, Kabul., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fundamental Principles: Democratic Republic of Afghanistan. Ministry of Information and Culture, Publication Department., 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Afghanistan II (13 pamphlets and 1 bulletin) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Genesis of the Undeclared War Against the Democratic Republic of Afghanistan. Government Printing Press, Kabul., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Information Bulletin: Peace Solidarity and Friendship Organization of D.R. Afghanistan. Government Printing Press., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Judge for Yourselves! State Printing House, Kabul., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Karmal, Babrak. Babrak Karmal's Speech to the Eleventh Plenum of the PDPA, CC. Government Printing Press., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - March 8: Anahita Ratibzad's Speech on the eve of Women's International Day. Government Printing Press, Kabul., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Martyred for the Cause of the Truth: The true Moslems murdered by the "Mujaheddin." Democratic Republic of Afghanistan, Islamic Affairs Dept., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - On Events in Afghanistan. Novosti Press Agency Publishing House, Moscow. (2 copies), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pomeroy, William. Why Soviet Troops Are in Afghanistan. National Council of American-Soviet Friendship. (4 copies), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - White Book: Pakistan's Subversive Activities Against the Afghan Revolution. DRA Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Information and Press Department, Kabul. (2 copies), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- AFL-CIO (17 pamphlets) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barbash, Jack. The Labor Movement in the United States. Public Affairs Committee, New York, NY., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Foner, Henry. Saul Mills and the Greater New York Industrial Union Council, CIO. Reprinted from Labor History., 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gaer, Joseph. When a Worker Needs a Friend. CIO Political Action Committee, New York, NY., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hirsch, Fred. An Analysis of Our AFL-CIO Role in Latin America or Under the Covers with the CIA. San Jose, CA., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hudson, Roy. The C.I.O. Convention and National Unity. Workers Library Publishers, Inc., New York, NY. (4 copies), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Morris, George. Labor Unity What AFL-CIO Merger Means for Workers. New Century Publishers, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Murray, Philip. The Case for Labor. CIO Department of Education and Research, Washington, DC., 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Organize the Unorganized the CIO Its Progress and Its Goal. Congress of Industrial Organizations., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Should Labor Have a Direct Share in Management?. CIO Department of Education and Research, Washington, DC., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The AFL-CIO and Civil Rights. American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations, Washington, DC., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Changing Situation of Workers and Their Unions. ALF-CIO Committee on the Evolution of Work, Washington, DC., 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The CIO and the Negro Worker Together for Victory. Congress of Industrial Organizations, Washington, DC., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Position of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union in Relation to CIO and AFL 1934-1938. International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- AFL-CIO History (12 pamphlets as well as a constitution and a handbook) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CIO What it is...and How it Came to Be. Committee for Industrial Organization, Washington, DC., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Democracy and the Free Labor Movement. American Federation of Labor, Washington, DC., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - For a Powerful United A. F. of L., 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Green, William. A Democratic Institution. American Federation of Labor, Washington, DC., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legislative Achievements of American Federation of Labor. American Federation of Labor, Washington, DC., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Morris, George. The C.I.O. Today. New Century Publishers, New York, NY., 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Morris, George. Where is the CIO Going?. New Century Publishers, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Organized Labor's Modern Wage Policy. American Federation of Labor, Washington, DC., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The CIO Must Fight for the People!. United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE), New York, NY., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Africa (19 pamphlets) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Africa at the 24th CPSU Congress. Novosti Press Agency, Moscow., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Against Apartheid and Colonialism in Africa. World Peace Council, Helsinki., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Communist Call to Africa., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Etinger, Y. African Solidarity and Neo-Colonialism. Novosti Agency Publishing House, Moscow., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ford, James W. Imperialism Destroys the People of Africa. Harlem Section of the Communist Party, New York, NY. (1 original, 1 photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Forward to May Day - Forward to Namibian Independence (from Workers Unity). South African Congress of Trade Unions., 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hunton, Alphaeus. Africa Fights for Freedom. New Century Publishers, New York, NY., 1950 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ledda, Romano. Social Classes and Political Struggle in Africa. New England Free Press, Boston, MA., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Monteiro, Tony. Africa and the USA The People Must Unite. National Anti-Imperialist Movement in Solidarity with African Liberation, New York, NY. (2 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pittman, John. Africa Calling: "Isolate the Racists!" The Liberation Struggle in Southern Africa. New Outlook Publishers, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "South Africa Has Robbed Us of Our Country". Africa Defense and Aid Fund of the American Committee on Africa, New York, NY., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - That They May Live African Women Arise... Women's International Democratic Federation, Berlin., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Woolbert, W.G. and M.S. Look at Africa. Foreign Policy Association, New York, NY., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Yergan, Max. Africa in the War. Council on African Affairs, New York, NY., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Woll, Matthew. Steps Necessary for High Post-War Employment., undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Africa: Liberation Struggle I (15 pamphlets) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Davidson, A.B. Two South Africas: Social-Political and Cultural Role of the Republic of South Africa in the African Continent. Papers Presented by the USSR Delegation Il International Congress of Africanists, Moscow., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - DuBois, W.E.B. But a Few Years Africa in Battle Against Colonialism, Racialism, Imperialism. African American Heritage Association, Chicago, IL. (2 copies), circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fyodorov, L. Africa Forging Unity. Novosti Press Agency Publishing House., undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Monteiro, Tony. Africa Demands Freedom Now. National Anti-Imperialist Movement in Solidarity with African Liberation, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Numade, N. Three Essays on the African Revolution. New Century Publishers, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Potekhin, I.I. Africa: Ways of Development. Nauka Publishing House, Moscow., 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Smirnov, S.R. State Formation in the Course of Liberation Wars. Papers Presented by the USSR Delegation Il International Congress of Africanists, Moscow., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Wilkerson, Doxey A. The Negro People and the Communists. Workers Library Publishers, New York, NY. (3 copies), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Africa: Liberation Struggle II (14 pamphlets) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Davis, Ben Jr. The Negro People and the Communist Party. Workers Library Publishers, New York, NY. (3 copies), 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ford, James W. The Communists and the Struggle for Negro Liberation. Harlem Division of the Communist Party, New York, NY., undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Wilkerson, Doxey A. Why Negroes Are Joining the Communist Party. Communist Party, New York, NY. (4 copies), 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Africa: Neo-Colonialism (2 pamphlets) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Neo-Colonialism and Development in Africa. World Peace Council. Helsinki., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Neocolonialism in Action: How the Imperialists are Bludgeoning and Plundering the Developing Countries. Institute of International Politics and Economics of the GDR., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Africa: Solidarity (6 pamphlets, 2 reports, and 3 issues of the Tricontinental Bulletin) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - African Solidarity and Neo-Colonialism. Novosti Press Agency Publishing House, Moscow., undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - David and Goliath Collaborate in Africa. The Africa Research Group, Boston, MA., undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - End Colonial and Racial Crimes!. Novosti Press Agency Publishing House, Moscow., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Monteiro, Tony. Africa and the USA: The People Must Unite. National Anti-Imperialist Movement in Solidarity with African Liberation, New York, NY. (2 copies), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)